We're glad to have Angela
Fan today with us here.
And she's a research scientist
at Meta AI Research in New York,
focusing on research in
text generation mainly.
And currently, she's
working on language modeling
and developing the line
AI agents meta products.
And recent research products
include No Language Left
Behind, which we'll be
talking briefly about today,
universal speech translation
for unwritten languages
as well as Llama2.
So give it up for
Angela, I guess.
All right, thank
you all so much.
So yeah, when I got this
email, I was like, oh,
I should probably
talk about lama2,
but then I noticed
you have Sharon,
who is like a 10x
better speaker than me.
So I was like, OK,
maybe not Llama2.
But then I thought I maybe would
cover this project that we did
called No Language Left
Behind, which could be also
very relevant to this class.
And so when you think about
a lot of text generation
technology, most of it,
until fairly recently,
has been really
focused on English.
But there are actually more
than 3,000 written languages
worldwide.
And for me, this is extremely
personally meaningful
because, actually, English
is my third language.
So it's really important--
yeah.
So it's really also very
personally meaningful.
And when you think about some of
the multilingual technology that
permeates, it's not like we've
never worked on multilingual.
Actually, when speaking
about generative AI,
I actually think
translation is one
of the most commercially
successful and widespread
applications of generative AI.
I mean, ultimately
translation models.
They are like conditional
language models.
And so when you think about
traveling or something
like that, or my sister
is taking Spanish, so just
like doing her
Spanish homework, we
have a lot of tools
that exist today.
So things like Google Translate
cover around 130 languages,
Microsoft Translate about 110.
This might be a
little bit outdated,
since I pulled the
statistics a little bit ago.
But the project for
No Language Left
Behind, it started
from a very simple ask.
OK, there's 3,000
languages worldwide.
Maybe it'll be like pretty
hard to get to all 3,000,
since some of them are pretty
rare, and not spoken by many.
But there are still hundreds
of languages spoken by millions
and millions of people.
And so we were like,
OK, no big deal.
Let's just start from the
100-ish that we have today
and just go for like a doubling.
What would it take
to actually be
able to double this
kind of coverage?
And, of course, just saying that
you support a bunch of languages
is not the goal.
We actually want to create
high-quality safe translations
that would be usable by people.
Just like if you're
going on vacation today,
you're instinct is to
whip out your phone
and get on the
Google Translate app.
And so the backdrop
to this project
was that there was actually a
lot of progress in translation.
So historically, there's
been a lot of focus
on what we call higher
resource languages,
and these are not
necessarily languages
that are spoken by the
most people in the world.
But when we say
higher resource, it
means the most amount of data.
And so you can
think about things
like Euro Parl or translations
from the European parliament.
And those served
as the foundation
for a lot of
translation development.
And more recently,
there's been a great focus
on low-resource languages.
And it's been driven across
the research community
with groups like Ghana NLP,
Masakhane, America's NLP.
And these are all really
exciting developments.
And so these have led to a
lot of development of new data
sets as well as criticisms
of existing data
sets, and also work
on new languages,
and usually, languages
that people speak
and they care a lot about.
And we found this
really, really exciting.
And so looking at a lot
of this, a bunch of us
got together at fair and
started thinking like,
OK, we actually speak some
pretty low-resource languages
from Catalan to
Assamese and so on.
And so we started this as
kind of like a big passionate
research project.
And so today, I want
to cover a little bit
about our high-level approach
to this problem, which is
a little bit interdisciplinary.
I want to talk about
how we actually
created the data sets to be able
to support this kind of work.
Of course, I want to
talk about the models,
since this is a class
about transformers.
One note here, I
think that's actually
very interesting in
terms of translation
as a research direction is that
actually, a lot of innovations
have been done in translation.
The original transformer
paper, I think, is one of them,
and which makes always
translation a quite interesting
area to work on because I feel
like it's a very mature research
area as well.
So it is like, OK,
if your architecture
works in translation, it
probably works very generally.
So that's also one of the
things that excites me
about translation research.
Then I want to talk
about evaluation,
like how are we actually
measuring and ensuring
the quality of
these translations
are good and safe for people.
And then I want to
end with a little bit
of high-level thoughts about
future directions and things
that I hope that we can
work on in the future.
So I want to start
with our approach.
I think the most important
thing in research
is to know that we're
working on a real problem,
especially when it's
really close to people,
like translation.
And I think in many
areas, like when
I was working on
On-Device AI, for example,
I feel like I had like a
research problem in mind,
but it was very,
very disconnected
from the practical problem
of actually putting models
on phones.
And so this was something that
was really important to us.
And so we actually
started the project
by focusing on a
social-sciences-type approach
or sociology-type approach.
And we actually did
a lot of interviews
with low-resource speakers.
And so we met with about 44
different native speakers
that spoke 36 different
languages across North America.
I will say that a lot of them
are immigrants to the US,
since that was the easiest
kind of cohort to recruit.
And we learned a lot
of different things
about how they approach
low-resource languages,
but also the technological
need that they have.
Because I think it's
easy to be like, hey,
I have this cool background.
I have this cool problem,
and I want to solve it.
But I think it's very important
to actually talk to the people.
This is a problem that
needs to be solved.
And so we learned that there's
great fear, in general,
that low-resource languages
might be undergoing
a state of decline, partially
because a lot of education
is shifting to languages
like Hindi or English
or Mandarin Chinese,
for example.
And there's a lot of excitement
to be included in existing
translation systems.
And people said,
they have always
tried to use Google Translate
or Microsoft Translate
in their existing languages.
But ultimately, they
found that the quality
is really insufficient
for reliable usage.
So if you think about--
well, I was going to say
when I was in high school,
but you all are probably like
substantially younger than me.
So maybe 10 or so
years ago and you
try to use Google Translate
for your Spanish homework,
your Spanish
teacher could always
identify that it was not a
human-written translation.
And so you would get marks
off, but that's not really
the case for some of the
high-resource languages today.
And so I think, as with all
things in machine learning,
it really starts from
a data perspective.
Why can't we just train
models in hundreds
of languages or large language
models in hundreds of languages?
It's because we don't have
the data to support it.
And so I want to talk
first about evaluation data
sets because I think
it's extremely important
to nail evaluation.
And then I'll talk
about training.
So for an evaluation data
set for this work we started,
this FLORES effort, it stands
for Facebook Low Resource.
I guess we're called
Meta now, but I
didn't think FLORES was
a very good renaming.
So we'll still
calling it FLORES.
So this was something
we originally
started for just two languages
in this first paper, EMNLP,
many years ago.
So it was just for
Nepali and Sinhala,
and we later extended it
to incorporate two more
languages in a release.
Afterwards, we thought
a lot about OK,
FLORES was really useful
for the community.
How can we extend
it to 100 languages?
And so that was his
follow-up work that we did.
I think we had an ACL or WMT.
And then in this project,
we were like, OK,
how can we go from FLORES-101
to FLORES-200 to really go
for the doubling effect?
And so what is FLORES?
Well, it's in the name.
It's a focus on
low-resource languages.
So we do include some
higher resource languages
like German or Hindi or so on,
almost for calibration effect
as well.
But the majority of the
focus is on these lower
and mid-resource languages.
It's the first large-scale,
many-to-many machine translation
evaluation data set, which
means that we take all
of the sentences in English.
And then we translate them to
all of the languages, which
means that you would
be able to evaluate
any cross pair of languages.
So for example, like
Chinese to French.
I lived in France
for many years,
so it's very personally
relevant to me.
Of course, 200 languages,
also in the name.
There's a broad diversity of
different domains and topics.
I think this is important when
designing an evaluation data
set, which is very top-of-mind
for anybody interested
in language modeling research,
because the way people train
machine translation
models and the way people
use them are often
very different.
And so if you only benchmark
your data set, for example,
on news, which is very common
in translation research,
then you don't really
pick up the fact
that people talk about such
a wide variety of things
and have different
casual conversations
that they need translated,
official documents, and so on.
It's also
document-level data set.
This is not something that I
think the community is broadly
leveraging right now, but
the way it's translated
is that you can have
document-level context.
And so translators are
provided the entire document
to translate from.
And we also provide the entire
document for evaluation.
And we translate
multiple sentences
from the same paragraph.
And so this was like a
potential research direction
that we wanted to
make sure we covered,
models that needed
potentially more context,
because a lot of
translation work
is done at the sentence level.
So how do we actually
ensure that this data
set was high-quality?
So the first step is
that we take a document.
Well, actually, first step is
alignment on language standards.
So this is very
important because when
you're translating
French or Chinese,
I think most people have a
strong understanding of what
it means to produce a good
French or good Chinese.
And there are a lot of
professional translators
hired in these languages.
But when you go to lower
resource languages,
it's not necessarily
the case that there's
like a glowing
translation industry
around translating a
lower resource language.
And so one of the first
things is actually
to align on like, what is
a high-quality translation?
And so there's actually
a lot of challenges here.
So there are certain
low-resource languages,
where there's different
competing language standards,
or there's very high
variance in different regions
on how languages are spoken.
And so this step is a
pretty critical one.
So then what we do is
we take the document.
We send it to one
group of translators,
and they do the first
translation step.
Then we do some
automatic checking.
If the input
sentence was 10 words
and the output
sentence is 300 words,
it's like, most likely
something went wrong.
And so we send that back.
Otherwise, we'll send it onwards
to a separate, completely
independent set of
translators that do review.
And so they try to rate
the quality of this.
And if the quality doesn't
pass a sufficient bar,
it gets sent back to the
original set of translators
to edit.
And they go through and
address all of the feedback.
And then if it's good enough,
then it enters our data set.
And so there's many
challenges here.
The first one, of
course, is just
finding translators, and also
finding more translators.
There was a certain issue
that we ran into, for example,
that in a certain country, the
internet was not available.
And so it's a lot
of recruitment.
The other one, of course,
is language standardization.
I think I briefly
mentioned this before,
but there's a lot of different
challenges in just understanding
like, what is a
high-quality translation?
For example, the
low-resource language Breton.
There's two competing groups
on how do you write Breton.
So it's very difficult to
resolve some of those things.
And the final thing
is that there's
actually a lot of variation,
even in languages like Arabic.
Moroccan Arabic is very
different from Jordanian Arabic
and so on.
And there are also
certain regions
that they speak
the same language.
But due to historical reasons,
they write in different scripts.
And so one of the
things we actually did
was like, if there are languages
written in multiple scripts,
we actually supported the
collection of a multiple script
evaluation.
And I think this is really
important because if you're
building an
underlying technology
and you only choose
one, then I think
you risk just naturally
supporting one over the other,
when we really should be a more
neutral technology provider.
And so this is something
that we export a lot
as well as exploring
different variants of Arabic.
This is also open-source.
If you just go to this
link, you can just
download all of the
text files for this.
With evaluation done, I
want to talk a little bit
about how we collected some
of these training data sets.
The first thing I
want to talk about
is this data set we
created called NLLB-Seed,
and the idea of this is,
it's a really seed data
set of high-quality
translations and languages
that really don't have anything.
Why?
Because, well, you can't
start from nothing.
You got to bootstrap
from somewhere.
A lot of people have been using
the Bible as a way to bootstrap,
but it's very limited domain,
obviously, very religious text.
And so we created this
data set, NLLB-Seed,
for languages that really
don't have anything
to get started from.
It's only about 5,000 sentences,
so it's nothing crazy.
But it supports a lot
of different use cases,
like training language
identification models
or sentence encoders,
n-gram language models,
all of these things that
I'm about to talk about
in our data set pipeline.
So it covers 43 languages,
about 6,000 sentences.
And the way we decide
to sample it is focused
on really general content.
So Wikipedia has this
article of like, hey,
if you're going to start
like a new Wikipedia
in your new language--
I think Wikipedia has 309-ish,
Wikipedia's last I checked.
Here's a list of articles
that every Wikipedia
in a new language should have.
And so that's where we sampled
this original content from.
And, of course, it's
also open-source
if you want to download it.
So what we ended up doing to
get large-scale training data
is using mining.
So this is not something we
pioneered in this project.
We have a bunch of
different previous work.
So we started from WikiMatrix.
We were like, hey, there's
a lot of different sentences
in Wikipedia on
different languages
that we should be
able to match up.
And so we try to do
that with Wikipedia
to get machine
translation training data.
We extended that to the web
in the CCMatrix project.
And then we extended it to
very, very large scale mining
on all cross pairs
in this project
on beyond English-centric
multilingual machine
translation.
We really tried to ditch English
as a central pivot language.
And so the way this
whole data mining
thing works is that it
focuses on sentence alignment.
So everyone is probably
super familiar with this
because this is how language
models are built now.
It's like, you take common crawl
or any other open-source dump
of the web--
I don't know-- like
RedPajama, or whatever
you want, CCNet, whatever
you want to use these days.
And you take all of the data.
You extract all of the text.
A lot of HTML parsing,
and so on, goes into it.
And the idea is that we want to
try to find matching text that
could be a translation.
So we shatter it
all into sentences.
We embed them with different
sentence encoder models.
And then we do a match
to try to understand
in a multilingual space
if the sentences match.
And so one of the biggest
challenges to this
is that the quality of
the sentence encoding
is very important.
So if your sentence encoding
is not very accurate,
then it's impossible to match
in this dimensional space
the idea of the
meaning being the same.
And so one of the big things we
try to do here in this project
was try to improve the quality
of the sentence encoders.
And so one of the big
things that we did
was train sentence encoders
with masked language modeling.
You see that on the left.
But we also use
multilingual distillation,
which you see on the right.
And so previous approaches
to sentence encoders
and the trend in the research
community for a while
was to really try to embed all
languages in the same sentence
encoder model.
So projects like XLM-R, for
example, are in that direction,
I think, is pretty widely used.
The challenge with
this when you're
training a low-resource
model is that a lot
of your high-resource
data just overwhelms
your low-resource data.
And so you don't end up with
a very high-quality sentence
encoder for those languages.
So what we ended up doing is
we had a multilingual teacher
model, and we distilled
a bunch of student models
that are specialized to
different language families that
are low resource.
And so this enables the
quality to be pretty high.
So the way that
distillation works
is that the teacher and
the student model both
see the same data.
And then we try to minimize the
cosine loss between the sentence
embeddings that they produce.
I think an important question
that you can ask here
is like, why do you need to
do multilingual distillation?
Why can't you just train a bunch
of different student models,
like one per language family?
Why even care
about distillation?
And the reason is
because if you're
going to use a bunch of
sentence encoders for mining,
the important thing is that they
all exist in the same embedding
space.
If you train one separate model
and another separate model,
there's nothing
constraining them
so that you can mine all of
the data against each other.
And so one of the
things we found
is that by starting everything
from the same teacher model
and trying to use this
cosine loss to minimize
the distance between
embeddings, you
are able to have this
constrained space where
you can mine every language
against every other,
even if you have
different student models.
And so this graph
on the y-axis, it
shows the error rate of mining.
And so lower is better.
And on the x-axis,
it shows a bunch
of different
low-resource languages.
So for example, the
first one is Urdu.
The second one is Telugu.
Third one is Tagalog, and so on.
And so the gray bar here is
the original laser paper.
So this is a paper we put
out maybe in 2018-ish,
and we had all of
these languages.
We counted them as included.
But as you can
see, the error rate
is extremely, extremely
high for these languages.
So even though
they were included,
couldn't really be
used for high quality.
And the blue bar
is the laser model
that we trained based on the
technique I just described
in the previous slide.
And you can see that--
I think the most important
point is that you can barely
see the blue bars.
So it was very effective, even
for these previous languages
that people had thought we
had previously embedded.
And then so now, how
does this kind of thing
fit into a whole data
pipeline around this approach?
So one of the most
important things
is when you download
the data from the web,
you don't really know
what language it's in.
And so this is part of all
of the large-scale data
cleaning that goes into training
large language models today.
And so the way we identify
different languages is,
is through simple
classification models
called Language
Identification Models.
And I think it's a
classification model.
And so people think it's
easier than it actually is.
But I think some of
the major challenges
are that there are so
many different languages.
They're written in
many different ways,
and web text is very casual.
And so it can be very
difficult to actually train
a good classification model
that can generalize to that.
And so what we did is we
had our LID training data.
And we produced a Language
Identification Model, LID.
And then we actually did human
evaluation to label errors
coming from the LID system
to iteratively improve
this on web text itself,
to improve the quality
of the specific model.
Then after we produce
this LID model,
then we insert all
of our Common Crawl
where the web
arrow is coming in.
And we do a ton of
filtering and cleaning.
And this produces a huge corpus
of different monolingual data
that you can then use
for training anything.
Afterwards, we
train our encoder,
what I described on
the previous text.
And then we convert
this monolingual data
into what we call Mined Bitexts.
So these are a huge data
set of things that we think
are translations of each other.
And then, finally, what
we do is we actually
try to validate that these are
real Mined Bitexts by training
very small bilingual translation
models in order to see
what the quality is like.
And I think this is important
because the data development
cycle and the end task that
it's being used for, you don't
want to completely separate it.
An analogy to large
language model training
today is that when you're
doing your pre-training,
you don't want someone to
just deliver you a data.
The data mix of your different
data sets is very important.
And it's pretty similar here.
And I think one
of the highlights
that we did here
is really focused
on the human evaluation of the
language identification model
because that actually
improves the quality of all
of the underlying data if
you just more accurately know
what language it's in.
And this entire data
pipeline is actually
open-source in this library.
And we had an NLP
paper describing it.
The reason why I thought
this was important
is that because I think
data cleaning is actually
such a fundamental
underlying thing that
drives model quality and
people's data pipelines.
It's like I have this
script and this other thing,
and this other thing.
And so it's actually,
I think, very
important to be able to
recreate it and rerun it
as part of almost
your research that you
would do as follow-up work.
And so this is why
we open-sourced it.
A few reflection things.
For low-resource
languages, even though we
did a large-scale mining,
I think monolingual data
is the limiting factor.
There are many
languages that do not
have a huge amount of
text written online.
And so it can be very
challenging to get
a large amount.
Further, I think languages
and unique scripts
can be extremely hard to get
good representations of if you
don't have very much data.
There are certain languages
as well where they
were historically
written in a new script,
but now the
government would like
to write it in a totally new
one, like the Ol Chiki script,
for example.
And so there's not
a lot of content
to represent these
scripts, so it's
hard to learn representations.
And then further, a
lot of the content
we create, even after mining,
it's a fairly limited domain,
often religious content.
So with data discussed, I
want to segue a little bit
into some of the modeling
work, just to start
with a high-level picture.
I think there's three
major challenges when
you talk about large-scale
multilingual modeling,
and these pretty much apply
to language models as well.
The first one is effective
data augmentation
for low-resource languages.
How can you prevent the
low-resource language data
from just being
completely drowned out
by the time you've seen all of
your words of German or Russian?
I think there's also a question
of scalability of the model.
So even if you train
very large-scale models,
how do you prevent
the representations
of different languages from
interfering with each other?
And that leads to the last
point as well of like,
if you give the model
very limited capacity,
then, of course, it may
not have the capacity
to model all of these
different languages.
And so you also
need to accelerate
the scale of the model.
And so preliminary for those who
may not have seen a translation
system before--
I don't know how many of
you that practically is--
so we use standard
sequence-to-sequence models.
So the input text,
the choral thing,
is what you want to translate,
enters a transformer decoder
model.
That, then, with the
attention mechanism,
goes to a transformer
decoder model.
And then it decodes
autoregressively
the actual translation, which
you can see here in yellow.
And so I want to talk a little
bit about how the data looks
as we feed it into the models.
So there's a few
different ways that you
might want to think about data.
So you want to be like,
OK, did a human look at it
and decide that these two
sentences are translations?
Or are they noisy?
Also, is it limited in size?
Another thing you
can think about
is, is the data quality
dependent on some other factor?
And so that's the
model-dependent thing.
In which case, the
data quality may
be capped by the quality
of that dependency.
And so I think you can think a
little bit the ideal data set.
It would be like, humans have
reviewed every bit of it.
It's not noisy at all.
We have an infinite
amount, and it
doesn't have any dependencies
on any other models.
It's just pure quality.
But in reality, closer to
what we have are these.
So we have a bunch of
different data sources.
We have the seed data that I
discussed way back in the talk,
where it's a small amount
of really high-quality,
human-aligned data,
but the only problem
is that it's limited in size.
It's 6,000 sentences
per language.
We have the PublicBitext.
So this is data that people
have created over many years
of working in translation.
You can download it from the
opus corpus, for example,
mostly has not been
reviewed by humans,
so pretty extremely noisy.
And many languages, it's
just coming from the Bible,
so the size is quite limited.
You have our Mined data.
So this is not
human-aligned either,
but it does have a
model dependency.
It's dependent on the quality
of the sentence encoders.
And we have two other sources
of data from back translation.
So the idea of back
translation, it's
a model augmentation
technique heavily used
in machine
translation, where you
use a model to produce pseudo
translations like silver data.
And we use two
different techniques
to produce these back
translations that
also are dependent on
the underlying model used
to make the translations.
So this is a picture of a
high-level different data
sources and how
you want to think
about the quality and
the different axes.
And so if we put them all
together, what do we get?
So the y-axis here is the
number of training pairs,
and the x-axis here is the
languages sorted by resource.
So you can see on
the left-hand side,
you have your low-resource
languages like Wolof.
And on your right-hand
side, you've
got your high-resource
languages like French.
The peak is English, of course.
And so if you just look at
what's available publicly,
this is a distribution you get.
And you'll see a huge, huge
fall-off pretty quickly.
And then if you add in the data
that we have created from mining
and back translation,
our goal is basically
to make the distribution
a little bit more uniform.
It's very hard on the
extremely low resource
side, of course, but to make
it a little bit more uniform so
that you don't just immediately
overfit on your low resource
languages before
you've even seen three
shards of your German data.
With that kind of
data strategy in mind,
I want to talk a little bit
about mixture of experts.
So this is something that we
explored quite aggressively
in the translation space
for a number of years.
We could have this
equal conversation
about some of the
debates going on like,
do you want sparse or
dense, architectures
for large language models?
But essentially,
mixture of experts
enables massive
scale because you
don't have to just scale
your dense trunk model.
But you can have a bunch of
different separate experts
that you activate per token.
It also allows you to
avoid language interference
because the idea is that
the different experts,
they could specialize
to specific languages.
Unfortunately, it adds
a ton of capacity,
so it becomes pretty
easy to overfit.
So I'm going to talk a little
bit about this overfitting
phenomenon.
So the top set of graphs that
we're going to talk about
is for the language Congo.
And then the bottom set
of languages is French.
So you really want to compare
a low-resource language on top
with a high-resource
language on bottom.
So if you just take your dense
model, traditional transformer
sequence-to-sequence
architecture,
that's this graph
that you're showing.
So there's a little
bit of overfitting
on the low-resource language,
but you can pretty much
regularize this with
standard dropout techniques.
So there's not a big
problem and on French.
You basically have
no real problem.
However, the minute you switch
from like a dense architecture
to a token-level
MoE architecture,
you just experience
a massive overfitting
on the low-resource language.
So the green line here is just
demonstrating without dropout
the overfitting.
And then if you add dropout,
you get a little bit better
performance, but it's still
overfitting quite a bit,
essentially by 12k updates.
There's no real point
in continuing training.
You're burning GPU, basically.
And so one of the things we
actually worked on quite a bit
was trying to figure out how to
properly regularize these MoE
architectures with this
specific masking technique
on the gating function that
decides which expert to route
to in your MoE architecture,
to just try to pull back some
of this overfitting effect.
So if you look in the top-right
graph, the purple line,
you still see some
successful regularization.
Another thing that we did
to control the overfitting
effect-- it's actually quite
being used in language models
today as well-- is
curriculum learning.
And the idea of
this is, how are we
going to stage when
languages are introduced?
And so what we did was we
tried to train a vanilla model.
And then we started
to measure when
the languages begin to overfit.
And then we basically bucket
them into different sections.
And so for high-resource
languages like French,
you want to start it early.
And it needs to be
trained the entire way.
But for a lower resource
language like Wolof,
after maybe like 100k
updates, it's done.
So the rest of the time,
it's just overfitting.
And so it actually gets
worse the more you train it.
So what we did is we moved
some of those lower resource
languages, and we
inserted them much later
into the training schedule.
So you start training
your high resource,
then you start training
your mid-resource, and then
your low resource, and then
your very low resource.
And so by the end,
everything in theory
has trained and is not
as overfit as it would be
without this kind of technique.
So I want to show some results.
So first, I want to show
results on existing data sets.
So before we get
to 200 languages,
let's just talk
about 100 languages.
And so this is the
FLORES-101 devtest
it's important to compare
to this because this
is where existing benchmarks
in the community lie.
Whereas on 200, of course,
we can put up anything
because it's the
first work on that.
So the first column is
translating out of English.
So English to Chinese,
English to Icelandic,
anything like that.
The second column is
translating into English.
So Chinese to English.
The third column, xx-yy, is
translating any cross pair
not involving English.
And the last column
is the average.
So if you look at the
first set of rows,
this is a comparison
on models that
cover 87 different languages.
So there was this
paper, M2M-100.
There was also
this Deepnet paper.
So you can see the
average blue score.
Blue is a standard
translation metric,
essentially a metric
of word overlap.
So we're looking
at blue score here.
And so you can see the last
row, and it will be 200.
Even though we
cover 200 languages,
the blue score is substantially
above some of the existing work.
Now, if we look
at 101 languages,
only the DeltaLM paper
from Microsoft at the time
covered that number
of languages.
And so if you compare on all
of the different cross sets,
similarly, you see that this
no language left behind.
Model is much stronger
in terms of blue.
One thing, really quick, on the
variance of these blue numbers,
I think it's important
to understand,
is something statistically
significant or not?
I think about 0.5 blue
is the general plus-minus
that you'll see.
And so if it's above
that, it's usually
a statistically
significant improvement.
So now, I want to talk a little
bit about FLORES-200 results.
So here are similar, the first
chunk of columns translating out
of English.
Then next chunk is
translating into English.
Then you have your cross pairs.
And then you have your average.
So we have this
blue metric as well.
We also have a
character-level metric,
based on chrF plus plus that's
commonly used in the translation
community.
So I think, looking at
these numbers, of course,
there's no baseline work
to compare to unlike
on the previous slide.
And so when we get to human
evaluation and a little bit,
it'll be more concrete.
But I think, generally,
one of the rules of thumb
I have for these types
of numbers is around 30
is pretty reasonably
becomes usable.
And I think another
thing, like if you compare
these supervised pairs
to zero-shot pairs,
I think we don't
see a huge drop off
on zero-shot, which
indicates the model has
some sort of
generalization, even
if it didn't see that
translation pair directly
during training.
Another way to
calibrate some of this
is to compare to
Google Translate.
And so if you compare
to Google Translate,
No Language Left Behind
is quite a bit better
at translating into English, and
not as good as translating out
of English.
Although if you like
average across everything,
it's a little bit better.
I want to talk a little
bit about human evaluation
as well to complement
some of our discussion
on automatic evaluation.
And so I think
automatic metrics--
fast, really good for
research iteration,
impossible to move
forward without.
But human evaluation is
really the real deal here.
And so we had this
paper at AMTA on how
to make this human evaluation
very consistent and scalable
across different language pairs.
I think this goes back to
the evaluation data set point
that I was making at the
beginning of the talk, where
if you're a professional
German translator,
you're really good at
evaluating the quality
of your German translation.
But beyond that, there's
not a lot of consistency.
And if you evaluate translation
on a five-point scale,
like a five translating
between two languages
and like a three translating
between other two languages
like, are those
really comparable?
And so we had this entire
experiment methodology
on how we might want to
make this a little bit more
comparable.
So I want to show some
results now on this.
So the y-axis here--
so the metric is called XSTS,
some metric for how we're
doing this human evaluation.
The y-axis here is
actually the delta.
It's a five-point scale, so
it's a delta, not the raw score.
The x-axis here is a bunch of
different translation directions
that we evaluated.
So the gray set is
translating into English.
The green set is translating
non-English directions,
so like French to Wolof.
And then the blue set is
translating out of English.
And so what you're looking
for is a positive delta,
indicates that our modeling
architecture is much better.
So what the delta is between is
a baseline transformer model,
just trained on all of our data,
versus the final No Language
Left Behind model
that we created.
So the data is actually
the same for both of them.
That's how we get
all 200 languages.
So we're just measuring
here the human eval
of the modeling improvements.
And so you can see most of the
delta is pretty noticeable.
Some of them, not so much.
I don't know.
Zulu to English, we didn't
seem to improve very much.
But in general,
it's an improvement
detectable by human evaluation.
You might also ask, OK, what is
the statistically significant
difference here between
about 0.2 to 0.3
plus or minus is something
that's pretty noticeable.
And above 0.5, it's
very noticeable.
One of the things that I also
want to get at in evaluation
is that there's many different
facets of model evaluation.
And I think if you look at
all of the different LLM
leaderboards or the
transparency reports
or whatever, you begin to
internalize this pretty quickly.
But what we just looked at are
just very high-level summary
numbers, and they
don't really tell you
what exactly are the errors.
And is it ultimately
usable by people?
Is it a safe thing that
people can rely on?
And so one of the things
we really focused on
is user safety.
And some of that manifests
in some of the toxicity
work that we did.
And the driving thing here
is that not all errors
in translation are made equal.
So during COVID,
there was this one
that really went viral
circulating around,
but the message during COVID
is you got to wash your hands.
But the translation
producer was like, you
got to hold hands, which I think
is like exactly the opposite
of what you want to do.
And other types of
measurement errors
are really important as well.
So if you're telling someone
how far they want to go
and you're like, hey, you
want to travel 5 kilometers,
and then your translation
is travel 500 kilometers,
it's a completely
different type of issue.
And so what we did
for toxicity, which
is a big focus for
this work, is that we
collected different toxicity
lists for all 200 languages.
And so why do I care
so much about toxicity?
I think it's a
user safety thing.
So if you input some
perfectly benign text
and then the output
is profanity,
I think it's just like
really unexpected,
and it breaks a lot of
trust in the system.
And it's an extremely poor
experience for people.
That, being said, it's also a
very, very challenging thing
because it's extremely
culturally specific.
So things that are slurs or
insults in certain languages,
they don't really
generalize across cultures,
which means that
things like this
are very challenging to create.
And I also was very
interested in this direction
because I think it's
broadly useful for all sorts
of different type of detection,
things that you need to do,
and also mitigation.
And so even though
we develop this
in the context of
translation, it
can be used very broadly in
other types of NLP applications.
This is also open-source.
You can download it.
You have to type in a
little password that's
in the github repo just so
that you don't accidentally
download and realize you
have files of curse words
all over your computer.
So I want to end a little
bit with some thoughts
about future directions.
And before I get there, there's
a 190-page paper that writes up
all of this in far greater
detail in case you're curious.
So a few future
directions that I
think I'm really interested
in, and some of these
are also very applicable
to things like speech,
is that I think one of them
is more explicit multilingual.
So I think a lot of
approaches to multilingual
have been like, hey, we
have this thing that's
working well for one language.
Let's try to scale it to a
bunch of different languages.
And then we're going to put
them all in the same modeling
bucket and just hope
that the model learns
all of these different
representations.
But I think there's a lot of
potential room for explicitly
bringing in, like the fact that
you know it's multilingual,
and so the architecture more.
And so it's possible to capture
more nuances between languages
or different relationships
between languages.
And the other one is continued
support for everyone.
I think it's like something
reflecting on this project,
is that going from 100 to 200
was already pretty challenging,
but going beyond a
lot of the techniques
that we developed here are
not necessarily that scalable.
This is actually what
inspired some of our work
on speech translation as well.
So if you recently saw
the seamless M42 release
or the unwritten
languages-- we did
a lot of modeling of Hoquiam.
And I think that goes
into this direction
really well because many of
the languages that people want
to use are spoken first
languages, and not
necessarily primarily written.
And then I think the
last thing that I'm still
really passionate about is
continued increase ease of use
and training of these
models, and democratization
for the community.
So one of the things that we
tried to do in this work is just
really, really clearly write
down everything that we did
and open-source, even the data
pipeline and things like that.
And so that's where you
get all of the repos
that I linked in,
like a huge write-up.
But I think if
someone were to try
to reproduce this for their own
language-- and many people have.
I'm not saying that hasn't been.
But it's like, if you
wanted to do this,
it would be extremely,
extremely hard
because there's just like so
much different things going on.
So I think most
of what we've seen
is people have
downloaded the base model
and fine-tuned it for
their own language.
But it's pretty
hard to just like
add on many, many more
languages to the system
because of how complicated
all of the moving parts are.
And so I feel like something
for the translation community
overall is, how do we simplify
a lot of these things?
And I think that's where a
lot of fundamental modeling
innovation could help us get to.
And so, yeah, I got a
chance to give this talk,
but, of course, the
work is like being
done by a huge team of
people that I've cited here.
And yeah, if you want to use any
of this or read more about it,
everything is linked from
this main github repo
here in fairseq.
And you can click on
everything else afterwards.
But yeah, maybe I'll
go back to Steven
if we have any questions
or anything else like that.
All right.
No, thanks for the great talk.
Yeah, if anybody
has any questions,
feel free to unmute and ask.
Did you consult with a
lot of native speakers
for profanities in
this type of stuff?
How were you able to get access
to the low-quality languages
or low-resource languages, and
make sure the translations are
correct?
Yeah, yeah, that's a
really good question.
I mean, I think it's the
most important to consult
a bunch of native speakers
across the entire development
process.
So part of our original
thing was interviewing
a bunch of people
to understand what
they're looking for in a
high-quality translation.
And then we have an entire
professional translation team
hired, which took quite
a long time to find,
to consult with
along the process.
And then right now, we also
have some of the things
like toxicity lists, are
open to the community.
So if you make like
a pull request,
we try to validate that.
It's like a useful addition, and
then try to merge it in as well.
We have a question in the room.
Let's see if it comes over soon.
Go ahead.
So I'll see, Steve.
Yeah.
So did you spend most of your
time in a data pipeline space?
Yeah.
Yeah, good.
Yeah, a good question.
I think the question
is, did you spend
most of your time in
the data pipeline today?
It ended up being about 50-50
data, or more like driving work,
and then 50-50 on the other side
like modeling and evaluation
work.
Because once the
data is set, then
there is a lot of iteration
on the modeling side
to figure out, OK, how much
of the data should we use?
How should we portion the data?
How do we prevent overfitting?
What is the right architecture?
But a lot of work
goes into the data.
Because I think if you don't
have high-quality data,
you just can't get a good model.
And for data mining, how
do you mine the data?
Do you use Selenium?
Or how do you mine the web?
Yeah.
So for the web, we
start with Common Crawl.
So we downloaded all of the
different dumps of Common Crawl.
And then we use HTML parser.
I think, now, if you download,
for example, the RedPajama
data set, they've done a lot
of this parsing and stuff.
And then we have large-scale
pipelines that are set up.
You can use Spark, for example,
to process these things,
to split all of the
different sentences
out, run your language
identification.
You can do different
heuristic cleaning.
There are certain
languages where
it's actually very challenging
to identify what is a sentence.
I think in Thai,
there is no period.
So you have to use
a different models
to identify what is a sentence
and parse some of those things
out.
And then we end up with
our monolingual data dump.
But what is Common Crawl?
Is it software that you
use for data science?
Oh, yeah, yeah.
Common Crawl is like
an open-source version
of the web that runs, I
think, maybe quarterly.
I would have to check.
But yeah, if you go
to commoncrawl.org,
you can download it.
But warning, it's very large.
I have a question.
You might have
mentioned this briefly,
but I'm wondering how ChatGPT
and GPT-4 does on this.
Does just more scale
and pre-training data
help as well for low-resource
machine translation?
Yeah, yeah, good question.
Actually, there have
been some studies
done on how these systems work.
I think for
high-resource languages,
it's actually quite
beneficial to scale up.
I think part of that is
because the models have
some innate generalization,
and so one of the challenges
that people talk about different
things in different languages.
So seeing that knowledge
in another language
can actually help
the generalization.
But on low-resource languages,
yeah, the performance
is pretty difficult, especially
on some of these translation
benchmarks.
I also think that
language models,
in terms of being trained
for a translation objective,
tend to score worse on
translation benchmarks
because language models
are approximately
capturing the same thing.
Whereas translation
models, you're
really try to align the
meaning a little bit more.
But yeah.
So I think for low resource,
still pretty challenging.
But yeah.
One thing that's interesting
is for most English language
models, they can actually
do a reasonable job
at producing other
languages because it's
impossible to get rid
of other languages
in your English-specific data.
So things like French or
German will work reasonably.
So just to clarify.
You said language models trained
with a translation objective
do better because--
They tend to do better.
If you fine-tune for
the translation task,
it will tend to do better.
Well, that makes sense
compared to, for example,
some few-shot
in-context examples.
Exactly.
Now, one other
question is, do you
see this being similar
to, for example,
fine-tuning on particular
expert domains, which might also
have less data and
low resource, and as
well as domain-specific
jargon and so forth?
Yeah.
I mean, I think if we were
to restart this project now,
I think that would be one of the
first things we also explored
or at least an extremely
strong baseline, where
if you take some of the data
and you try to fine-tune, or try
to do domain adaptation,
I think that's also
where some of the
retrieval-type approaches
go in for translation, but also
large language modeling work,
where you try to have a separate
domain that you can retrieve
some text in for adaptation.
I think all of those approaches
are pretty promising.
Oh, great.
Any other questions?
One quick one on the point
of zero probability on one
of the slides.
I think you showed
some peak results
with zero-shot that were higher
than just the base model.
Do you think that's
because there might still
be some overfitting on those
low-resource languages?
Yeah, good question.
So for our
large-scale mining, we
don't mind every single
possible cross pair.
So like Icelandic
Wolof, it's probably
like not like the most
in-demand translation direction.
And so we did not
mind all 200 times 200
because it's really producing
a combinatorial explosion.
And so that's where the
zero-shot results come from,
where we don't have training
data directionally in that pair,
but the model has seen both
the input and the output.
And so I think those
results are pretty good.
Well, they're good for
certain language languages,
which I think goes to show
the generalization capability.
And it's not as critical to
have every single pair covered,
but many of them
are not as good.
And so you see overall the
performance is lower, even
though on certain languages.
It can perform better
than you expect,
but that's because it has
seen the input and the output.
It's not zero-shot on
completely unseen language.
I have a question.
But I wanted you to
also do something
related to transcription
or audio information.
Yeah.
Good question.
So in this project, no.
Not so much transcription.
But we had a follow-up work
that we released, actually,
just like a month
or so ago, called
SeamlessM4T, which is like a
joint model for both speech
and text translation.
And that's where we do leverage
a lot of audio transcription
because that also has--
it helps us bridge the
spoken data and the text
data to leverage both
of them together.
Thank you.
But just to clarify the
supervised fine tuning,
it worked better compared
to other methods?
So actually, in this work--
it was a couple of years
ago now, so supervised fine
tuning wasn't as common
as it was now.
But I think in the
literature, if you
want to use a large language
model to do translation,
it's currently best, yeah, if
you do some supervised fine
tuning.
I'm just wondering about that
because the way, as humans, we
don't just learn
by looking at pairs
of the same thing in
different languages
and memorizing how to map
from one to the other.
We learn in a more
unsupervised way,
where if we know
both languages, then
we can naturally
translate between them.
But I guess it makes
sense for an LLM
why having supervised
examples would help.
Yeah.
I mean, I think as the base
foundation model continues
to improve in quality, I think
that's where the quality will
probably improve, and you don't
need less and less fine tuning.
I mean, I think that's
like the OpenAI approach.
If you have the best
foundation model,
then you don't need as much
domain-specific fine tuning.
And I think at the
start when I started
working on text
generation, there
was translation researchers
and summarization researchers
and question-answering
researchers.
And they worked very
differently But now,
it's all driven by the
same underlying thing,
and you're not like a
specialized summarization
researcher anymore.
I think that makes
a lot of sense.
Do we have any other questions?
Any question?
Any more in-person questions?
I don't think so.
OK, great.
All right.
Well, thank you, Angela,
for the very interesting
and a great talk again,
and for taking the time.
Yeah.
We hope that you
can keep in touch.
And if anybody has
any other questions,
feel free to get in
touch with Angela.
All right.
Thanks so much for
having me today.
Bye, everyone.